<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Letter from the fleet, with a diurnal account of the military affairs between the English and the Dutch, from Friday the 3d. of June, till Thursday the 9th. of June. Relating the taking and firing many of the Dutch since the late fight, the blocking up Flushing and other harbours, the landing of men at the Texel aud [sic] in Zealand, and the opposition made by the Hollanders.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87973</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E699_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207047</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866123</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866123</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166562</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87973)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166562)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 108:E699[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Letter from the fleet, with a diurnal account of the military affairs between the English and the Dutch, from Friday the 3d. of June, till Thursday the 9th. of June. Relating the taking and firing many of the Dutch since the late fight, the blocking up Flushing and other harbours, the landing of men at the Texel aud [sic] in Zealand, and the opposition made by the Hollanders.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date on p. 6: 9 June, 1653.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 13 1653".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anglo-Dutch War, 1652-1654 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Naval battles --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166562:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER From the Fleet, with a DIVRNAL Account of the Military affairs between the Engliſh and the Dutch, From Friday the 3d. of <hi>June,</hi> till Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the 9th. of June.</p>
            <p>RELATING The taking and firing many of the Dutch ſince the late fight, the blocking up Fluſhing and other harbours, the landing of men at the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xel and in Zealand, and the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition made by the Hollanders.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:166562:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:166562:2"/>
            <head>From our Fleet riding upon the coaſt of Holland came as followeth.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſignall victory which the Lord hath been pleaſed to give over our Enemies, I hope will raiſe up the hearts of all Gods people in <hi>England</hi> to praiſe him, not onely in words, but in deed &amp; truth; and I wiſh that it may be recorded amongſt the chief of thoſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies that God hath beſtowed upon his Saints, that all poſterities to come may give him honour, and that the preſent age may not be ſo ſtupid as they have been, let them take notice of, and keep in perpetual memory thoſe which the Lord hath wrought even in our dayes; and likewiſe be aſſured that he will goe forward with his worke untill he hath perfected the ſame, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:166562:3"/>all the Treaſons, Plots, or Conſpirtions of men; God hath taught us notable Leſſons of this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, of which I ſhall onely minde you of one or two and proceed to Intelligence.</p>
            <p>The very day that the Treaty began at <hi>Vxbridg,</hi> that ſame day we loſt a ſtrong gariſon, but the very day that we brake off Treating with the Kings party, a ſtrong Caſtle was delivered up unto us. And that very day that a Letter came to the late Parliament from the <hi>Dutch</hi> with ſome overtures of peace, one of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall ſhips belonging to this Commonwealth was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by fire.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Diurnall Account of ſome proceedings between the Engliſh, and the Dutch, from Fryday the third of June, till Thurſday the ſeventh of June, <hi>1653.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe third of June in the evening. The Enemy making all the ſaile he could to get homewards, the ableſt of our ſhips which ſuffered leaſt damage in the two dayes ſight; made after the Dutch fleet, and did good execution upon them for many Leagues purſute and ſome ſhips of ours that had received pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice in their Maſts and Tackling, together with our wounded men (which were about 236) and about 1130 priſoners which we had taken of he Dutch) were ſent away for the Engliſh ſhore. Gen. <hi>Blake,</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:166562:3"/>and Gen. <hi>Monke</hi> Anchered this night between <hi>Oſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd</hi> and the <hi>Wellnigs.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <head>The names of the ſhips which came in with Gen. Blake were theſe.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Eſsex Frigot,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hampſhire Frigot,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The William,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Eagle,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Culpeper,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th whelpe,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Phenex,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Storke,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Hopefull Luke,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Imployment,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Proſperous,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The John and Abigale,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Swan.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>June the forth. In the morning Inteligence was brought that <hi>Tromp</hi> was neere <hi>Flankenburgh,</hi> &amp; it was thought he would make way towards <hi>Fluſhing</hi> which is one of the beſt Ports they have. This day we had brought into us ſeverall Dutch veſſels, and Scouts were ſent forth ſeverall wayes for making a further diſcovery of ſuch of the Dutch as had eſcaped away in the fight into any of their Ports, as likewiſe to catch up any of their Merchantmen that ſhould be ſliping into any of their Harbours, and it was reſolved by a Councell of War that our maine Fleet ſhould follow the purſuit of <hi>Tromp</hi> and ſuch as had eſcaped with him, and ſo towards <hi>Fluſhing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>June the fift. We were againe within ſight of ſome of the Enemy, but he crept away by the <hi>Sholes</hi> and <hi>Sands</hi> where we could not come at them; ſomething
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166562:4"/>like the Highlanders in <hi>Scotland</hi> who ſave themſelves by their inacceſſable holds.</p>
               <p>This day a view was taken of many hundred ſick &amp; wounded ſouldiers ſouldiers of the Dutch who were taken by our fleet, and care taken for ſetting them on ſhore in their own Country, and they being in pain and miſery are likely to give their other Country men the trueſt information after their vapouring againſt Dover, which (though it ſavoured rather of impudent inſolency then of valour, yet) was printed a huge and mighty victory at the Hague.</p>
               <p>June 6. Our Fleet came near the Texel, and the ſick and wounded ſouldiers of the Dutch before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, were put into long boats and other veſſels (upon their parole) and lanced out to go on ſhore, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king forth towards the land, they (being deſcried from the Caſtle) the Dutch let fly many great guns at their own men, and upon this they received a great allarum into the Country, about which time the main body of our fleet appeared within ſight, at which the people cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out they were betrayed and undone, and in ſuch an amazement they continued.</p>
               <p>The next day we did not onely take many of their ſhips near their own harbours, but fired others, and ſent many hundred great ſhot on ſhore amongſt them, <hi>and now judge you whether we are not even with them for their attempt upon Dover;</hi> and we are upon another de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to find them work at home, not doubting but by the next you will hear that ſome of their ſtrong holds are in our poſſeſſion.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:166562:4"/>
               <p>This day ſome of our Scouts brought in two Dutch veſſels, and divers water ſhips and others came from the Engliſh coaſts with ſupplies of ſuch neceſſaries, as we ſtood in need of they alſo bring us news that many ſupplies are coming after which will be very ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for carrying on of the work in hand.</p>
               <p>The greateſt part of the Dutch fleet which eſaped is is gotten into the harbour at Fluſhing, where we hope to keep them from doing further miſchief upon the ſeas againſt England.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter from Dover, dated, the 9th. of June.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe three or four days together many ſhips which came out of the River of Thames, paſſed this way to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our fleet which is on the Coaſt of Holland, wherein went a conſiderable number of ſouldiers, and a great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of powder, ſhot, and Ammunition, as likewiſe a great number of Shovels, Spades, Pick-axes, and other neceſſaries for land ſervice, we hear alſo that the like ſupplies are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them from ſeveral other parts belonging to this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth. Some wounded ſouldiers are gone up to London and others remain here under cure, the State having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſpecial care for ſending down able Chyrurgians into theſe parts to cure ſuch as ſtand in need of their help.</p>
            <p>This day arrived a veſſel here which landed ſeveral perſons, which ſay that they have been with our fleet, &amp; one of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166562:5"/>them reports that Gen. Blake and Gen. Monk, are before Fluſhing, and be heard at his coming away that ſome of our men were landed in a kind of a ſmal Iſland near Fluſhing in Zealand, where no horſe could get to them, and if we could keep it, it would conduce very much to the effectual blocking up of that City, and ſecuring their ſhipping in the harbour. Some of our fleet is ſent out ſeveral ways to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the preparations and motion of the enemy, and we hear they are in a great diſtraction among themſelves, and Trump whom not long ſince carried a Broom in his Top-Maſt to ſweep the Seas, dares not ſo much as ſweep his door, ſcarce daring to ſhew his head. The Officers in general ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe one another, and the common people blame not onely them but their high and mighty <hi>Hogen Mogens.</hi> I truſt the Lord will put a ſudden period to theſe wars, to the praiſe of his great Name, and the good of his ſervants that deſire to walk uprightly before him, which is the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your aſſured friend, T. Leigh.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>9 June, <hi>1653.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
